公元4世纪晚期  罗马帝国江河日下
The late fourth century A.D. the Roman Empire began to crumble.
地处于埃及行省的亚历山大港
Alexandria, in the province of Egypt
如同落日余晖
still retained some of its luster,,
该港拥有古代世界七大奇迹之一
possessed one of the Seven Wonders of the ancient world:,
享誉盛名的亚历山大灯塔
the legendary lighthouse
以及人类早期历史上最伟大的图书馆
and the biggest library known.
这个书馆不仅是文化宝库  也是宗教象征
The library was a not only cultural but a religious symbol,,
多神教徒在此参拜他们的祖先神
a place where the pagans worshiped their ancestral gods.
如今传统的多神教徒与犹太教徒
The traditional pagan worship in the city now coexisted,
在此共存
with the Jews,
同处于此还有屡禁不止的
and an unstoppable religion up to now banned,,
基督教
Christianity.
少有傻瓜会扪心自问
How many fools do you think have asked themselves?
星星为何不会从天空坠落
why don't the stars fall from the sky
可你不同  你受过智者的教育
But you, who've had the teachings of the wise,
你知道星星只会升起或落下
You know that the stars move neither up nor down.
自东至西转动
they merely revolve from east to west,
沿着最完美的轨迹
following the most perfect course ever conceived,
做圆周运动
The circle.
风暴佳人
圆周运动主宰宇宙
Because the circle reigns in the heavens,
因而星星永不坠落
the stars have never fallen and they never will.
但是在地球上呢?
But, what about here on Earth?
在地球上  物体自由降落
Here, bodies do fall.
但是他们的运行轨迹  不是环形而是线形
But their movements are not circular but linear.
再看一次
Watch again.
别捡  放那儿
No, leave it.
那么
So,
你们认为在地面之下究竟蕴藏着
What mysterious wonder do you all think might be
何种神奇物质?
lurking beneath the Earth
使得人类  动物
that would make every single person and animal
所有的物体以及奴隶适得其所
and object and slaves circular?
那会是什么呢?
What might it be?
是重力  老师
The heaviness, lady.
不对
No.
辛奈西斯
Synesius.
因为他们的重量
The weightiness.
不对  你们说的是一样东西
No, you're both speaking about the same thing,
但你们都没有切中要害
but you're not talking about the primary course.
你们有没有人想过你们的
Have any of you ever wondered that your,
你们的脚
that your feet,
your feet
站立在宇宙的正中央
are standing on the very center of the cosmos
而宇宙承载万物
that holds all things together
并将万物紧密相连
and pulls them together
如果没有中心
If there were no center
那么宇宙将会混沌不清
then the universe would be
无穷无尽  无状之状  杂乱不堪
shapeless, infinite, formless, chaotic.
无论我们身处何方
Will it make a little difference,
都将毫无二致
if we were here or there or anywhere?
那我们不降临人间岂不更好
And we'd all be better off never have been born.
公元391年  亚历山大图书馆
Library of Alexandria 391 A.D.
神  我们之父
God, Our Father,
乃万物之主
Lord of the universe,
万物之源
origin of all things,
宇宙之永恒能量
eternal force of the cosmos,
万事万物在此有始有终
where everything has its beginning and everything its end.
全能的塞拉皮斯
Almighty Serapis
伊希斯
Isis
荷鲁斯
Horus
阿努比斯神
Anubis
以及所有凡间与天上
and all the other gods we ask for your protection.
给予子民保护的诸神
both in heaven and on earth,
市集上出事了
I don't know what's happening in the market.
我知道你对我也有感觉
I know you also feel something.
我看出了
I've seen.
请转告主人我们要走了
Tell the master we're leaving.
难以置信
Can you believe?
他像我示爱还把我当成他的战利品
He was courting me as if I'm one of his conquests.
真是有其父必有其子
This Orestes is as foolish as his father.
如果我建议他移情至另一位
I already suggested that he devote his heart to another muse
姿色更甚于我的女神
one more beautiful than I.
-谁?  -缪塞克
-Who? -Music.
音乐
Music?
他可没像你笑得这么开心
He didn't find his music.
本来是227  怎会变成16呢?
What happen? 227 ever become 16.
看这个  这里是14
Look at this, it's 14.
他们的生活习性与人类无异
They behave like humans!
他们吃喝享乐  骄奢淫逸
They eat, drink and fornicate!
如果我的诸神也吃喝享乐  骄奢淫逸
If my gods  eat, drink and fornicate
岂不快哉
good for them.
不是这样的  不是
Know this,Know this,
你们崇拜的形象没有一丝神圣可言
you who console yourself with pagan images.
不管是男人女人  还是飞禽走兽
Men, women, birds, reptiles!
塞拉皮斯  塞拉皮斯
Serapis! Serapis!
谁会信仰把花盆当做皇冠的神呢?
Who could trust the God, need a flower pot for a crown?
你们这些基督徒啊
Hey you, Christians
罗马帝国让你们幸存于此
how arrogant you'd become now that the,
你们却变得如此狂妄自大
Empire allows you to exist.
我的祖父曾看见他们
My father's father saw them
在竞技场里被屠杀并用来喂狮子
slaughtered in the circus and fed to the lions.
打住  打住  看着
Enough! Enough! Watch.
看着
Watch.
我将穿越火坑
I shall now walk across the fire.
若我主是
If my God,
若我主是真神  我将会毫发无损
If my God is the true god, I shall suffer no harm.
然而如若你的主存在
If however, your gods exist
我就会像只猪一样被烤死
they will roast me like a pig.
你
You,
你真勇敢
You're a lie!
你会被烧死的
你会遭到报应的
You'll get what you deserve.
现在我们来看看  你是否能穿越火坑?
Now, let's see if you can walk cross the fire.
你们想干嘛?
What are you doing?
住手  你们不能这样  放开他
Stop, you can't do that! Let the man go.
闭嘴  多神教徒
Be quiet pagan
否则把你也拖进去
or we'd call you in as well.
这是谁的?
Whose is this?
我得重复多少遍?
How many times must I repeat myself?
今天  基督徒当众烧伤了一名男子
Today, the Christians burned a man.
就在广场中央
Right in the middle of the Agora!
我的屋子里严禁出现这种东西
I will not have this in my house!
赛昂家严禁此物
Not in the house of Theon!
给我
Give it to me.
Give it to me!
主人  望您开恩  对此既往不咎
Master, I beg mercy for your slave girl.
达乌斯  起来
Davus! Get up.
这与你无关
You have nothing to do with this.
我也是一名基督徒
I too, am a Christian.
你说什么?
What did you say?
我也是一名基督徒
I too, am a Christian.
连我也一并惩罚吧
Punish me for the both of us.
他们妄想教我们什么是仁慈
So, now they presume to teach us mercy.
-拿鞭子来  -父亲
-Get a whip. -Father!
请您冷静冷静  好吗?
Please wait until you calm before you,
父亲  我求您了  我求您了
Father, I beg of you. I beg of you
他真的被燃烧的光亮包围吗?
wrapped in a blazing brightness.
傻子  那是真正的火焰
It was the flames, stupid.
那他为什么没有像多神教徒那样燃烧?
Then why didn't he burn like the pagan?
告诉我啊
Tell me.
请你回避一下
Leave us,
过来
Come here.
跪下吧
Kneel.
你真的是一名基督徒吗?
Tell me, is it true that you're a Christian?
我不知该怎么说  女主人
I don't know what to say, Mistress.
什么意思?
Why not?
如果我说是  那就是欺骗您
If I said yes, that would be a lie.
如果我说不是  那就是欺骗主人
If I said no, that'd mean I lied to my master.
我不知哪个情节更严重?
I don't know which one's worst.
那你就该缄默不语
Then you should say nothing at all.
好了
There.
谢谢您
Thank you.
我想让你知道主人对此很失望
I want you to know that the Master is upset with himself about this.
那是什么?
What is that?
是我做的小玩意  女主人
Something I made, Mistress.
这看上去像是一个
But it looks like a,
这到底是什么?
What is it?
这是托勒密的天体系统
It's Ptolemaic System.
的确如此
It is.
这是你做的吗?
Did you do this?
这是地球
Earth
她是宇宙的中心
is the center of the cosmos
而环绕四周的有
and revolving around it
太阳以及5大行星
the Sun and the five wanderers:
水星  金星  火星  木星  土星
Mercury, Venus, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn.
并没有遵守圆周运行轨迹的规律
Obstinately disobeying the law of the circle.
然而托勒密却向我们证明
Nevertheless, Ptolemy shows us that
他们遵守圆周规律
they do obey.
他们之所以绕圈运动
The fact that we see them move in a loop
是由两个天体环形运转合力而为
is due to the joint effect of two circles.
其中一个绕地球旋转
One that travels around the Earth
另一个沿着较小的圆形轨迹自转
and another lesser circle prophet to each wanderer.
看  那是本轮
Look, the epicycles.
你们所看到的并非真正的规律
See, it's not heaven or earth.
只是双眼蒙骗了我们
But our eyes that deceive us.
说的真好  达乌斯
Well said, Davus.
你的讲解证明
I'd like you to know that your exposition shows me
你比在座的某些人更加用心
that you've been paying closer attention than One or two,others here.
听着  上帝在造物之前
I tell you, the gods should have consulted me
都应该先征询我的意见
before they created anything.
你这从何说起  俄瑞斯特斯
Why do you say that, Orestes?
所有的这些都太古怪了
It all seem so whimsical!
为什么是两个天体  环形运转合力而为呢
Why the joint effect of two circles?
如果行星不按自己的本轮公转
Wouldn't it be more perfect, if the wanderers didn't wander,
而只按一个环形轨迹公转  不是更合理吗
and a single circle gave sense to everything?
俄瑞斯特斯  你有什么资格  评判上帝的杰作
Orestes, by what authority do you judge the work of God?
我哪儿得罪你了吗?  基督徒
What is wrong with you, Christians?
难道人都不能开口说话了吗?
Can a man no longer open his mouth in this city?
你批判天地万物  你批判我们的主
If you criticize creation, you criticize our Lord and you offend us.
因而你冒犯了我们
You should move out to the desert.
你该搬到沙漠里去
You won't hear anything,
这样你永远都不会听到这些逆耳之词
to offend you out there.
你们不知所云  所有人都如此
You know nothing of what you speak. None of you.
辛奈西斯  欧基里得的第一公理是什么?
Synesius, what is Euclid's first rule?
你为什么问这个?
Why the question?
只要回答我
Just, answer me.
那个
If,
等于同量的量
if two things are equal to a third thing,
彼此相等
then they are all equal to each other.
很好
Good.
你们都和我非常熟识吧
Now, are you both not similar to me?
是的
Yes.
那你呢?  俄瑞斯特斯
And you, Orestes?
也是
Yes.
在此我向你们郑重声明
Now, I'm actually saying this to everybody here in this room.
我们要团结而不是分裂
More things unite us than divide us.
无论外面事态如何  我们都亲如手足
Now, whatever maybe going on in the streets. We are brothers.
我们亲如手足
We are brothers.
我希望你们记住
I want you to remember
我们并非奴隶或者乌合之众
that brawls are for slaves and periphera.
现在我们用热烈的掌声
Now I think we should all honor Davus,
感谢达乌斯为我们讲解这些知识
with some very well earned applause.
他们会决定我们每个人是生是死
He'll judge us all alive and dead.
到了那个时候就为时已晚
And then it will be too late,
只有那些信仰耶稣的人
because only those who believed in Jesus
才能得到救赎
will be saved.
你们此时不皈依吾主
What are you waiting for?
更待何时
上帝之国在你我上方
The Kingdom of God is upon us.
你们听懂我说的话了吗?
Do you understand what I'm telling you?
听懂了
Yes.
你们明白要像个人吗?
Yeah but do you understand like men do?
或者你们不明白  就像只小羊羔
Do you, not your head, a sheep?
你在这看什么?
What are you looking at?
对  就是你
Yes, you.
你在这里干什么?
What are you looking here?
你是阿摩尼阿斯吗?
Are you Ammonius?
那个创造奇迹的人
The man who performed the miracle?
你想看到奇迹吗?
Do you want to see a miracle?
你是他吗?
Are you the one?
我是
I am.
跟我来
Come with me.
耶稣走遍加利利
Jesus went throughout Galilee
在各会堂里教训人
teaching in their synagogues.
传送天国的福音
Preaching the good news for you
医治百姓各样的病症
and healing the diseases of sick.
他的名声就传遍了叙利亚
News about him spread going to Syria
来自世界各地的人们  都慕名前来朝拜他
and people came from all over the world.
那是西奥勒斯
That is Theophilus.
我们的主教
Bishop.
因为天国是他们的
For theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.
哀恸之人有福了
Blessed are those who mourn
因为他们必得安慰
for they will be comforted.
温柔之人有福了
Blessed are the meek
因为他们必继承土地
for they will inherit the earth.
饥渴慕义之人有福了
Blessed are they which do hunger and thirst for righteousness
因为他们必得饱足
for they will be filled.
天主的世界
The word of God!
怜恤人之人有福了
Blessed are the merciful
因为他们必蒙怜恤
for they will be shown mercy.
清心之人有福了
Blessed are the pure in heart,
因为他们必得见神
for they will see God.
天主与你同在
The Lord be with you.
你是怎么穿过那火焰的?
So how are you able to escape the flames?
-天主与你同在  -也与你同在
-The Lord be with you. -And with you.
你觉得呢?我祈祷而已
What do you think I did? I prayed.
你可能都不知道该如何祈祷吧?
You probable do not even know how.
你那包里有什么?
What do you have in that sack?
-有吃的吗?  -这是我主人的
-Do you have any food here? -It's for my Master.
你没什么毛病吧?
What's wrong with you?
给你的话  我就得自己掏腰包了
I have to pay for that with my own money!
你要钱干什么?
What do you need money for?
看看他们的眼神
Look at their faces.
来
Here.
我想让你自己来试试
I want you to try it yourself.
然后我教你怎么祈祷
And afterwards I will teach you how to pray.
来
Go on.
-天主与你同在  -主保佑你
-The Lord be with you. -Bless you.
看见了吗?
See?
这就是奇迹
That is a miracle!
继续  接着发
Go on, keep doing it.
神与你同在
The Lord be with you.
谢谢
Please.
谢谢你
Thank you.
神保佑你
Bless you,
主保佑你
God bless you.
保佑你
Bless you.
奴隶
Hey, slave!
你叫什么名字?
What is your name?
达乌斯
Davus.
奴隶达乌斯
Davus the slave!
你像个真正的基督圣战士
Now, you look like a true parabolani.
一名真正的耶稣的战士
A true soldier of Christ.
他们说什么呢?
What are they saying now?
让他们跳舞
Telling them to dance.
他们正畅饮美酒呢
The men are now heavy with wine.
出海旅行
All aboard!
多么不幸的旅途
Oh what an unfortunate wreck.
救救你的奴仆吧
Save your servants!
第二幕结束
End of Part Two!
谢谢观看  各位观众
Thank you, audience, thank you.
我们现在要更换道具以及演出服装
Now, excuse the delay while we move things around,
希望大家谅解
and change our costumes.
不好意思
Good evening
原谅我的大胆
Forgive my boldness.
我是俄瑞斯特斯
I am Orestes,
俄瑞斯特斯家的儿子
son of Orestes.
我在这
I'm here to,
我在这想说出  对哲学家希帕蒂亚的爱意
I'm here to declare my love for Hypatia, the philosopher.
而她也深知这点
I mean, you all no doubt know
我采纳了她给我的建议
for some time now, following her counseling.
我投身于音乐当中
I have devoted myself to music.
希望在声音的和谐中寻求到一丝慰藉
In the hope of seeking solace in the harmony of its sounds.
但对我来说
But for me,
只有我倾慕的女士身上才有这种和谐
such harmony resides only in my lady.
所以
So,
我站在这只是为了
My purpose here is merely to,
献上我的音乐
offer my melody
并且希望
in the hopes of,
不用再说了
Stop talking.
那人肯定很有前途
That man will go far, I tell you.
如果我准备的是香蕉而不是无花果
He's my preferred fruit for the banana not the fig,
我早就扔在他脚下了
I would have already fallen at his feet.
你准备怎么回礼呢?
Wouldn't it be best to please him?
我吗?
Me?
怎么回礼?
How?
格来提  你能阻止的了你的女儿吗?
Granting him your daughter's hand.
难道你不打算让她嫁人吗?
Why don't you ever plan to marry her off?
希帕蒂亚嫁给一个男人  不读书不教书
Hypatia subject to a man? Without freedom to teach?
甚至不谈她的那些想法吗?
Or even to speak her mind.
我认识的最杰出的哲学家
The most brilliant philosopher I know
必须要放弃科学
having to give up her science.
不  那会让她生不如死的
No, that could be death to her.
没错  她的工作受人敬仰
It's true. Her work is admirable.
并且她德才兼备
That she's brilliant and virtuous.
可是赛昂
But Theon,
别忘了她的处境啊
She has not found her gift.
她只是个女人
Being a woman, I mean.
我们在天上的父  宅心仁厚
Our Father who art in heaven,
别让她答应别人
Don't let anyone have her.
求你别让她答应别人
Please, don't anyone else have her.
别让别人  别让她答应任何人
Don't let anyone else have her.
阿门
Amen.
早安  老师
Good day, lady.
早安
早安  老师
Good day lady.
昨天很多人看到  你们的同学把他的乐器
Yesterday, many of you would have seen one of your colleagues
献给了我
present me an ollos
我接受了礼物
I accepted the gift.
而今天我也想回送给他一份礼物
And today I wish to make him earn a gift of my own in return.
这是给你的
This is for you.
这是我的经血
It is the blood of my cycle.
俄瑞斯特斯你
Orestes you,
你说你在我身上找到了和谐
You say that you have found harmony in me.
那我建议你看看周围
Well, I am suggesting that you look elsewhere
因为我觉得周围也存在着
because I think that there is little harmony or,
和谐和美丽
beauty in that.
你觉得呢?
Don't you agree?
昨天我们谈到了阿波罗尼斯锥
Yesterday we were discussing the Apollonian cone.
我们讲了圆形  椭圆  物线
We discussed the circle, the ellipse, the parabola.
-今天我们来讲双曲线  -老师
-Today we will discuss the hyperbola. -Lady!
不好意思  老师
Forgive me, Lady.
奥林匹斯要你赶快到神庙去
Olympius requires your presence urgently in the Serapeum.
你们也是
You as well.
感谢主  感谢主
Thank you, Lord. Thank you, Lord.
感谢主
Thank you, Lord.
难道我们要忍受他们诋毁我们的信仰
How are we to enjoy them force feeding us the faith
习俗  甚至我们的人民吗?
and customs to people who until recently becoming outlaws?
-发生什么事了?  -这是种亵渎
-What's happening? -It's despicable. A sacrilege.
基督徒已经在城市广场集会了
Christians have gathered in the Agora.
他们在嘲弄我们的神明
They are mocking the gods.
我们必须阻止这些亵渎
We must put an end these insults!
他们也许不怕他
They may not fear him,
但他们一定会怕我们的利剑
but they will fear our swords.
等等
Wait!
你们要干什么?
Now, what is it you are going to do?
你们要去袭击他们吗?
Are you going to attack them?
只因为他们的无礼  就让他们血溅当场吗?
Are you going to stain your hands with blood for an insult?
是对神明们  对神明们的亵渎
To the gods! An insult to the gods!
如果你觉得他们过分
Well, if you think it is so outrageous then go
应该直接去通知本地的提督
and announce their acts before the prefect.
你好像在保护他们
One might think that you're protecting them.
我在尽力保护我们的学生们
I am trying to protect our disciples.
而你  在煽动他们成为野蛮的杀人犯
You, are inciting them to be violent murderers.
赛昂  作为首领  由你来决定吧
Theon, as director, you have the last word.
必须压制他们对神明们的不敬
The insult must be answered.
犹太教徒可以自愿参加
Those Jews amongst you do as you please.
这不是你们的战争
This is not your battle.
而这里的基督徒们
As for you Christians
你们最好去找你们的耶稣
you would do well to join those of your own fate.
你不能让我的学生走出这个建筑
You will not caused my disciples out of this house!
-塞拉皮斯万岁  -为了神明们
-Glory be to Serapis! -And all the gods!
等我的命令
Wait for my command!
在我们包围他们前  不会有人怀疑我们的
No one must suspect us until we have them surrounded.
这些剑是给奴隶的  奴隶们
The clubs are for the slaves. Slaves!
奴隶也要参加
Slaves are all for summon!
达乌斯  回去
Davus, back.
不  回去
No. Go back.
杀了基督徒
Death to Christians!
塞拉皮斯万岁
Glory be to Serapis!
让我们聆听她的声音
Let's listen to her now!
你们听到她的抱怨了吗?
Do you hear any complaint?
没有
No!
这一座也失声了
This one has lost her voice too!
他们的嘴不能说话
Their mouths do not speak,
他们的眼看不到东西
their eyes do not see,
他们的鼻子闻不到味道
their nose doesn't smell.
但多神教徒却要跪倒在他们面前
Yet still, pagans come here and kneel before them.
这是多么的疯狂啊
What madness is this?
顺从神明们的旨意
For the gods!
梅多罗
Medorus!
Take care of your master! Protect it,!
上帝只有一个
God is one!
打倒异教徒
Death to the pagans!
你  你看什么呢?  打啊
You! What are you looking at? Get there and fight!
打啊
Fight!
你聋了吗?  我说打啊
Are you deaf? I said fight!
我是个基督徒
I'm a Christian!
I am a Christian!
我是个基督徒
-什么是基督?  -基督是神
-What is Christ? -Christ is one!
打倒异教徒
Death to the pagans!
上帝只有一个
God is one!
不  不
No! No!
入口  我们必须守住入口
The entrance! We must defend the entrance!
怎么了?
What's happening?
我们的人被基督徒打败了
Our men are being sent back by the Christians!
父亲
Father!
没事  没事
It's alright. It's alright.
怎么了?
What happened?
是他的奴隶干的
It was his slave.
达乌斯  给我拿些布那些水来  快
Davus, get me some cloth some water, quickly.
父亲
Father,
辛奈西斯  我们得离开这里
Synesius, we must get out of here.
扶住他别动
Hold him still.
基督徒们来了
Parabolani are coming!
上帝与我们同在
God is with us!
哈利路亚  哈利路亚
Hallelujah! Hallelujah!
-关上大门  -别  我们的人还在外面
-Close the gates! -You know our men are still out there!
愿神明们保佑他们
May the gods protect them.
我说关上大门
Close the gates,I said!
别杀他  我们把他留作人质像那其它基督徒一样
Don't kill him! He'll be our hostage like the others.
大家都听见了吗?
Did you hear it everyone?
你抓到的所有基督徒
Any Christian you catch
如今都是人质
is now a hostage.
把我们的伤者送去寺院
Take our wounded to the temple
基督徒带到地下室去
and the Christians down into the cellars.
眼神好的人去墙上观察情况
And anyone with a good eye and a good aim up on the walls.
奥林匹斯
Olympius.
他是个基督徒
This one is a Christian.
没错  还有那三个
Yes, and those three as well.
如果他们是基督徒  他们就得去地下室
If they are Christians, they will go down to the cellars.
奥林匹斯
Olympius
如果你要囚禁我的兄弟们
if you are going to imprison my brothers
你就得把我也关起来
then you are going to have to imprison me with them.
如果必须如此  我会这样做的
If it is necessary, I will do that.
如果任何人
If anyone,
任何人
anyone,
敢碰我兄弟们一根指头
dare lay a finger on one of my brothers
我发誓我会刺穿他的身体
I swear I'll run in for you.
看
Look!
看这个
Look at this!
俄瑞斯特斯
Orestes.
谢谢你
Thank you.
什么时候开始?
Since when were there
有这么多基督徒的
so many Christians?
我们不得不和他们谈判了
We'll talk to them to negotiate.
我们在等什么?
What are we waiting for?
一个基督徒君主能做些什么呢
What can we expect from a Christian emperor?
除非我们收起刀剑
Except we'll be put in a sword.
至少我现在活了下来
Our sense of positive being the life when his verdict arrives.
小心
Here will do.
请大家都不要擅自行动
No one should leave the group, please.
他们要整夜祈祷吗?
Are they going to pray all night?
达乌斯
Davus.
待在这儿
Stay here.
这里很安全
It's safer here.
好好的留在这吧
Just stay with him first.
辛奈西斯  你要干什么?
Synesius! What are you doing?
老师  姐姐  母亲
Lady, sister and mother,
愿主祝福并保护你
May God bless you and protect you.
退后
Move back!
奴隶至死都吃这个
Slaves take it to the back.
奴隶排最后
Slaves get to the back!
三个一出现了
If this three one come out.
会是场灾难
It's a disaster.
父亲  你什么时候才能不掷骰子?
Father, why don't you leave the dice?
今天有人看过伤口了吗?
Have you been seen today?
-没有  -没有吗?
-No. -No?
让我看一下
Let's have a look.
孩子  向我保证
Promise me, my child, that,
在我死后  忘记现在这个愚蠢的老头
when I'm gone, you won't remember this foolish old man.
我保证
I promise.
记住我曾经的样子
Remember me as I was before.
记住那个还能思考  并且
Before when I could still think and,
我
I,
与你共事的我
work with you and,
记住我倾听你心事时的样子
I listen to you.
我怎么会犯下这样的大错?
How could I have been so wrong?
如今因为我的错误  让你被困在这里
Seeing you here locked up because of my,
父亲  请别说了
Father, please.
我希望你能够自由
I wanted you to be free.
我是自由的
I am free.
基督徒们
Hey, Christians.
Christians!
你们对上帝的那份自信哪儿去了?
What's that confident God of yours doing now?
进棺材吧  人渣
Maybe coffins for you, scums!
告诉我
So tell me.
那些神如今在哪里?
Where are the gods now?
他们在哪?
Where are they?
-可能也去找别人了吧?  -别人
-Might as well look for others. -Others?
哪一个?  基督徒的上帝吗?
Which one? The God of the Christians perhaps?
真是太放肆了
Such boldness!
你怎么想  老师?  你是如此的勇敢
What do you think, Lady? You are so bold.
把这盆火灭掉
Put the fire out.
你的确很大胆
You are indeed bold.
非常大胆
Very bold.
我一直在想你对我说过的那些事
I've been thinking about something you said to me.
我吗?
Me?
那天你质疑天体的运动轨迹
That day that you criticize the heavenly mechanism
而且你把它称为无稽之谈
and you called it whimsical.
是的  尽管
Yes, although,
其实
Actually,
我是在质疑托勒密的理论
I was criticizing Ptolemy.
他的本轮理论让一切都变复杂了
For complicating everything with his epicycles.
但我不确定  也许只是有些欠考虑
I don't know perhaps I'm just simple-minded.
不是
No.
天空之上
No, the heavens
应当是简单的
should be simple.
那么我是对了还是
So am I right or,?
如果
What if,
如果有个更简单的理论可以解释
What if there were simpler explanations
那些行星又当如何?
for the wanderers?
有的
There is.
但却太荒谬了  太陈旧了
But it is so absurd, so old.
没有人愿意相信它
That no one gives it any credit.
那是什么理论?
What theory is that?
你是在说阿里斯塔克斯吗?
Do you think of Aristarchus?
阿里斯塔克斯认为
Aristarchus maintained
地球本身在移动
that the earth moves.
而几大行星的奇怪行为
The strange behavior of the wanderers
仅仅是我们的星球
was nothing more than an optical illusion
在围绕着太阳运动时
caused by our movement
所产生的光学幻觉而已
in combination with Earth around the sun.
-以太阳为中心的模型  -是的
-Heliocentric model. -That's right.
太阳在中心
The sun would be in the center
仿佛它是宇宙众星的尊贵之王
acting as speaking of it as "King of the Stars".
-让我们变成了  -他的著作
-It would make Earth just,another wanderer. -His work was lost
在主图书馆的一场大火中被烧毁了
in the fire that destroyed the mother library.
这就是我们必须好好保护  这地方的原因
This is why we have to take great care of this place.
我们的图书馆
Our library
存留着人类的所有智慧
is all that remains of the wisdom of men.
但每次扔一个物体
But everytime you drop an object here.
谁在说话
Who speaks?
原谅我  女主人
Forgive me, Mistress.
我一直在听
I was listening.
说吧  达乌斯
Speak up, Davus.
如果地球在移动
If the earth is moving,
每当扔下一个物体
every time dropping an object it would,
它就会落到后面才对
fall further behind.
而风应该会保持迎面吹来
And the wind would always blow against us.
鸟儿会迷失航向
And the birds would lose their way in flight.
我跟你说过
I told you
阿里斯塔克斯的假说一点都讲不通
Aristarchus' hypothesis makes no sense at all.
我觉得你刚才说的可以被驳倒
I feel that what you just said can be refuted.
但现在我不知道如何去驳倒
But right now I don't know how.
给提督让道
Make way for the prefect!
让开
Make way!
给提督让道
Make way for the prefect!
让开
Make way!
大家都听着
Listen one and all!
请大家认真听并遵守君主的裁决
Prepare to hear and obey the verdict of our Emperor.
我  弗拉维乌斯・狄奥多西・奥古斯都
I, Flavius Theodosius Augustus
猎户区省的君主和最高行政长官
Emperor and Supreme Head of the provinces of the Orient,
最近了解到
having been informed of the events,
在亚历山大城发生的大事
which recently took place in the City of Alexandria,
特此宣布并命令大家
do hereby declare and command
这些起义者将会得到保护
that the insurgents shall be pardoned and freed.
而作为我宽宏大量的交换
In exchange for my generosity,
起义者必须马上
the insurgents will
离开神殿和图书馆
abandon the Serapeum and the Library immediately
同时允许基督徒进入
allowing the Christians to enter
并处理掉所有卷轴
and dispose off the premises
按其心意
as they see fit.
我们在期待什么?  他们会毁掉一切的
What are we to expect? They'll destroy everything!
多神教徒将会从后门离开
Pagans will leave by the stable.
那些书
The Books.
从那里你们会被护送至你们的家里
And they will be escorted to their homes.
马上执行
Obey this, instant!
派一半军队去那边
Send half of the regiment to the other side.
其余的等会过去
and send the rest later.
是的  长官
Yes, sir.
提督
Prefect.
我们这样坚持不了多久
We won't be able to contain this, not for long.
以十字架的名义  以十字架的名义
On the cross! On the cross!
留下那些次要的书
Leave the lesser works.
-哪些是次要的?  -拿走那些重要的
-Which are the lesser works? -Just take the important ones. The important ones.
士兵们后撤了
The soldiers are withdrawing!
奴隶
Slave!
-你们看到我的女主人了吗?  -快过来帮忙
-Have you seen my mistress? -Just get over here and help!
-我们拿不了这么多  -我们需要更多帮助
-They're not carrying so many. -We need more help.
请带我的父亲离开这里
Please go and get my father out of here.
快带他离开这里
Get him out of here now.
奴隶
Slave!
快  快走  快走
Go! Go! Go! Go!
快点  快点
Come on, quickly!
希帕蒂亚和他的学生还在正厅里
Hypatia and her students are still in the atrium.
他们疯了吗?
Are they out of their minds?
既然他们想那样  就随他们去吧
If that's what they want, let them burn.
快点
Come on!
Quickly!
小姐
Lady.
你去哪儿了?  把那个袋子捡起来
Where have you been? Pick up that sack.
-小姐我们得走了  -把那个袋子捡起来
-Lady We have to go. -Pick up the sack!
为什么到需要的时候  奴隶总是不在身边
Why are slaves never around when you needed them?
-我刚才在  -快点走啊  快点
-I was, -Move!, move your feet, move!
白痴
Idiot!
快跑
Run!
快点  没有时间了
There is no time!
老师
Lady!
别管这些了
Leave them.
上帝只有一个
God is one!
赶快
Run!
达乌斯
Davus!
你要去哪儿?
Where are you going?
-我们得走了  -达乌斯  你要去哪儿?
-We have to go! -Davus, where are you going?
如果他想为我们的神而死  就随他吧
If he wants to die for our gods, let him.
达乌斯  不要  不要这样做
Please, no. Please don't do this.
-快点  -达乌斯
-Come on! -Davus!
-达乌斯  不要  -快走
-Davus, no! -Come on!
以十字架的名义
God is one!
哈利路亚  哈利路亚  哈利路亚
Hallelujah, hallelujah, hallelujah!
奴隶
Slave!
达乌斯
Davus!
奴隶达乌斯
Davus the slave!
帮我弄倒这个
Help me with this!
帮我
Help me!
哈利路亚  哈利路亚  哈利路亚
Hallelujah, hallelujah, hallelujah!
多神教徒的人渣
Pagan sinners!
最沉重的伤痛都过去了
The Master's wound is festering.
我知道
I know.
达乌斯
Davus.
Davus!
你自由了
You're free.
走
Go.
走吧
从现在开始  在亚历山大
Hence forth, in Alexandria
只许举行基督教和犹太教的庆典
only Christian and Jewish worship shall be permitted.
禁止一切多神教的祭祀
Pagan sacrifices,
禁止膜拜多神教的象征物
worshipping pagan symbols
禁止参观多神教教堂
and visiting pagan temples shall no longer be allowed.
任何人敢这么做或注视它们的
Should anyone commit such an act or dare raise his eyes on the statues
古老神像  都将会得到严厉的惩罚
of former gods. He shall be punished without penance.
图书馆沦陷后  许多多神教徒皈依基督教
希帕蒂亚则继续教学和进行研究
而他之前的学生
成为了社会的中流砥柱
整个帝国被一分为二
许多基督徒认为  这是世界终结的前兆
于是决定过更神圣的生活
基督教圣战士穿梭在大街小巷
精力充沛地监督基督徒的品行
而犹太教徒的存在让他们无法释怀
该死的犹太人
Damn Jews!
他们只是一群没用的恶棍  畜生
They're just a bunch of good for nothing thugs, packed animals!
乔瑞恩  我亲爱的朋友  冷静点
Joran, my dear friend, calm down.
让西里尔主教解释一下吧
Let Bishop Cyril speak in his own defense.
提督
Prefect
我们那些神圣的圣战士
our blessed parabolani,
他们仅仅是
Whom he has just called
在打拍子而已
the Beast of Burden.
只是为了附和他们打拍子而已
Devote themselves true enough to carrying burdens.
他们都是残疾人或者病人
crippled, the sick, the lepers,
还有石头
And stones!
提督  他们带了石头
Prefect, they carry stones.
突然冲进剧院
And now, they burst into the theatre
他们知道我们无法自卫  还用石头砸我们
and stone us knowing we will do nothing to defend ourselves.
因为今天是安息日
Because it is the Sabbath!
在安息日这天  你们应该
On the Sabbath you should honor God
在犹太教会堂向主祈祷
in your synagogues instead stuffing yourselves
而不是在剧院欣赏戏剧
with sweet set of theater.
正因为这个石头才会落到你们头上
That is why the stones fell upon you.
提督  听到了吗?  他威胁我们  这太过分了
Prefect, do you hear that? Now, he's threatening us. This is too much.
友爱些  我们是合众院
Friends, there are more things that unite us than divide us.
我们是兄弟  我们全都亲如手足
We are brothers! We're all brothers.
没有犹太人哪会有你们基督徒?
Where would you Christians be without the Jews?
耶稣就是犹太人
Jesus was a Jew!
我发现了点东西
There is,something I find
可以反驳你所说的
disturbing in what you've told me.
-是什么?  -好吧
-What?  -Well,
西里尔为什么要开始清理城市?
Why does Cyril speak of cleaning up the city?
他已经拥有这么多了还不满足吗?
Is he not satisfied with what he already has?
他只想吓吓犹太人
I think he's just trying to frighten the Jews.
可为什么要当你的面说?
But why say it in front of you?
如果他想对付的是你  而不是他们怎么办?
What if really he was addressing you and not them?
我  为什么?  我和他一样都是基督徒
Me? Why? I'm as much as Christian as he is.
是的  可你忘记了
Yes, but you forget
你圈子里许多人不是基督徒
that many of us from your circle are not.
满帆  提督
And a full sail, prefect.
走吧
Let's go.
-亚斯巴修  准备好了吗?  -是的  女主人
-Aspasius, you ready? -Yes, mistress.
我要你拿着麻袋爬到桅杆的顶端
I would like you to take the sack and climb to the top of the mast.
好了  老师
And now, Lady,
你能给我解释一下  这是怎么回事吗?
Will you finally tell me what the point of all this is?
当亚斯巴修扔下麻袋的同时
When Aspasius drops the sack,
船在往前走
the boat will be moving forward.
因此麻袋
Therefore, the sack
不会掉在桅杆下
won't fall at the foot of the mast,
而是会掉得往后一些  我想大概
but will fall further back. I would say about,
大概会在这儿
about here.
这样做有什么意义吗?
And what is so special about that?
-太好了  -可你错了
-Yes! -But you were wrong!
是  但这是决定性证据
Yes, but this is definite proof!
决定性的  麻袋就像是在静止的船上那样掉下来
It's definitive. The sack behaved as if the boat was stationary.
那意味着什么?
What does that mean?
我不知道
I don't know.
但同样的原理也可以应用在地球上
But the same principle could be applied to the Earth.
它可能绕着太阳转而我们却不知道
It could be moving around the Sun without us realizing.
-阿里斯塔克斯的理论  -没错
-Aristarchus. -Exactly.
你为什么要那么执着呢  老师?
Why do you torment yourself with that, Lady?
托勒密理论虽不完善
Ptolemy's not perfect but,
但却很管用
it works.
俄瑞斯特斯  当时是你提出的
Orestes, but you are the one who,
提督  几年前你可没有这么务实
A few years ago, you weren't so pragmatic, prefect.
几年前我总是不经思考就发言
Well, a few years ago, I talked first and thought later.
我看到了仙王座三
I have Cepheus third.
三十七
37.
四十八
48.
金星和木星共同落在水瓶座里
Venus and Mars share house in Aquarius.
我父亲定会用美酒庆祝这种结合
My father would have celebrated such a conjunction with a good wine.
-星星永远不会落下  -真的吗?
-The stars will not fall. -Oh really?
是的  因为它们都镶在盒盖上
No, because they're fixed to the lid of their chests.
盖子会打开两颗心  然后耶稣就诞生了
The lid will open in two hearts and then Jesus will appear.
你说的是什么盒子?
What chest are you talking about?
你不知道宇宙是个巨大的盒子吗?
Don't you know that the universe is a gigantic chest?
天堂是盖子  地球是底部
Heaven is the lid on top and the Earth, the ground,
他们没告诉这个笨蛋地球是圆的
They haven't told this fool that the Earth is round.
地球是扁的
The Earth is flat.
你的脑袋是扁的
Your head is flat.
去看看圣经吧
Read the Scriptures!
如果地球是圆的
If the earth is round,
为什么住在下端的人们不会掉下去?
Why don't the people at the bottom fall off?
住在侧面的人呢?
What about the ones on the sides?
他们为什么不会滑下去呢?
Why don't they slide off?
想想看
Think about that.
达乌斯知道
Davus knows.
兄弟
Hey, brother.
你有什么看法?
What do you say?
地球是扁的还是圆的
Is the earth is flat or round?
只有上帝才知道这些
Only God knows those things.
放在地上别动
Leave them on the ground!
别管它们  它们就该放地上
Leave them on the ground! That's where they belong.
女士  请您不要灰心丧气
Lady, you must not lose heart.
今天在船上您已经取得了很大的进展
Today on the boat you made great progress.
为什么所有行星的亮度的变化
Why do the wanderers bury their brightness?
会如此变化无常
So unexpectedly.
更糟的是
And what is worse,
为什么太阳
Why does the sun?
为什么它的体积在夏天和冬天会不同
Why does it change size from summer to winter?
也许是因为它有时近
Perhaps because sometimes it is nearer,
有时远
and other times it is farther away.
可是  亚斯巴修
But Aspasius
看
Watch.
按阿里斯塔克斯的理论  太阳一定
According Aristarchus, the sun must be
是在万物的中心
at the center of everything.
而我们的地球
With us, the Earth,
绕着它沿圆周轨迹在公转
traveling in a circle around it.
因此  这就是关键
Therefore, and this is the key.
我们和它一直
We're always at exactly,
保持着同样的距离
the same distance.
如果按你说的  距离会改变
Now, if as you just said, we accept the changes in distance
那么我们就得
then we are forced to add
在地球轨道上加一个本轮
and epicycle to the Earth's orbit.
这样它才会时近时远
So it's going to be nearer and then it's going to be farther away.
这样我们就陷入托勒密的谜团里了  .
But now we fall into the same trap as Ptolemy.
-圈套着圈  -没错
-Circle upon circles. -Exactly!
我不知道如何解决这个矛盾
So I just do not know how to resolve this conflict.
你觉得我们能解决
I mean, the only thing we could do is,
把太阳从中心移走  那么
displace the sun from the center and well,
并非必须在中心
not to have a center.
这让我感到伤心  亚斯巴修
It breaks my heart, Aspasius.
告诉我  我该怎么做?
So tell me, what do I do?
休息一下吧  女士
Rest, lady.
基督圣战士
Parabolani!
-圣战士们  -怎么了?
-Parabolani! -What is happening?
圣战士们  快来救命啊
Parabolani, quick! Help!
圣亚里罕德罗着火了
St. Alexander's on fire!
着火了
It is a fire.
快点
Come on!
去提水  拿上水桶  拿着这个
Gather water! Get the water! Quick! Take this!
快点
Hurry!
快
Quick!
快  快点  跑快点
Come on, come on!
圣战士们
Parabolani!
圣战士们啊
圣战士  快啊
Parabolani, quick!
哪着火了?
Where's the fire?
在那边  那边
是犹太人  这是陷阱
Jews! It's a trap.
这是陷阱
It's a trap!
基督徒们
Christians, all.
昨夜是悲惨的一夜
Last night was a night to deplore.
现在我告诉你们
Now I say to you.
不要再为死去的兄弟们感到悲伤
Grieve no longer for our dead brothers.
不要哭泣
Weep not.
把眼泪留给其它人吧
Shed your tears for the others,
他们是刽子手
for they are executioners.
没错  没错
Yes, yes.
为那些干这件事的人哭泣吧
Weep for them. For those who have done this,
他们对上帝一无所知
Know not of God,
没有爱  没有同情心
nor of love nor of parity.
他们什么都不懂
They know not
因为今天他们重现了圣经里的情景
because it is they who repeat the words of the Scriptures
却对此一无所知
with no understanding at all.
他们只看到一个人
It is they who saw only a man
那就是上帝的儿子  站在他们面前
when the Son of God was standing in front of them.
也正是他们愚昧地嘲笑他
And it is they who in their blindness
还将他钉死在十字架上
mocked him and crucified him.
哭泣吧  哭泣吧  为犹太人哭泣
Yes Weep! Weep for the Jews,
他们害死了我们的主
those evil butchers of our Lord.
因为上帝
Because God,
上帝已经责罚他们了
because God, God, God has already condemned them.
这是上帝的旨意
It is God's will,
让他们成为奴隶
that they live as slaves
被诅咒  被流放  直到世界末日
cursed and exiled until the end of time.
被诅咒  被流放
Cursed and exiled!
女士  别停下  女士
Lady, do not stop, Lady.
所有的犹太人都想要复仇
Now all the Jews will want to retaliate.
恐怕你不清楚目前的状况
I'm afraid you don't understand what's really happening.
一切结束后  亚历山大  就不再有犹太人了
When this is all over, there will be no more Jews in Alexandria.
很抱歉这样冒失地闯了进来
I'm sorry for busting in like this.
老师  你不该冒险来这里的
Lady, you should the risk of coming here.
军队在哪?
Where are the troops?
为什么街道上没有士兵?
Why are there no more soldiers on the streets?
在那种混乱中  没有军队  可以控制整个城市
No army could contain that mob. The entire city is in a frenzy.
他要求杀光所有的妇女和儿童
Calling to the annihilation of women and children.
他是主教
A bishop!
-他是基督徒  -那就把他关起来
-A Christian! Then lock him up.
提督  你应该逮捕他
Prefect. You should have him arrested.
事情没那么简单
It's not so easy.
女士  西里尔知道我们有相同的信仰
Lady, Cyril knows they both share the same faith.
这让我们的长官进退两难
That places our prefect in a very awkward position.
如果他为犹太人辩护
If he defends the Jews, half the city will rise up
会有一半的市民反对政府
against his government.
我明白了
I see.
可如果现在你什么都不做
But if you choose to do nothing now,
我相信西里尔  会继续重复相同的事
I believe Cyril will continue to do the same thing over and over again and until,
直到杀光城里的最后一个人
until there is no one left in this city.
就没人可以让政府管理了
No people for this government to govern.
我太幼稚了
How naive of me.
我真幼稚  居然寄希望于最终的改变
How naive of me to think we have finally chose.
犹太人滚出去
Jews out!
他们先杀了他们
First, they kill them
然后埋了他们
then they bury them.
是昔兰尼的主教
The Bishop of Cyrene.
-他来这儿干什么?  -我去看看
-What is he doing here?  -I'll find out.
这是我的小亚历山大图书馆
It's my little library of Alexandria.
我在这里教孩子们知识
This is where I teach  the children.
阿波罗尼斯圆锥体
An Apollonian cone.
是的  我用它来教孩子们四种不同曲线
Yes, I built it to teach them about the four curves.
圆形
The Circle.
椭圆形
The ellipse.
俄瑞斯特斯应该早到了才对
Orestes should really be here by now.
物线
Parabola.
双曲线
And hyperbola.
真是美极了
It's truly beautiful.
我常看着它去思考
You know, I often look at it and I always wonder
为什么相同的圆轴?
why does the circle coexist with such
会产生如此多不同的形状
impure shapes?
不如我坐在这里再听你讲一次课
When I get to sit here and listen to you again.
看来让你无聊了
I bore you.
我已经很久没有教书了
It's been a long time since I've done anything but,
只是在研究天体系统上绞尽脑汁
beat my head against a stone.
然而却无人关注它的重要性
Anyhow, there are more important matters at hand.
我来晚了
Forgive me.
一个多神教徒控制着两个基督徒
Two Christians in the hands of a heathen.
真是不可容忍
It's an outrage!
-这里有多少?  -不知道  但会发出恶臭
-How many left? I don't know but it smells.
阿摩尼阿斯
Ammonius.
上帝跟你说过话吗?
Does God speak with you?
你总是这样
All the time.
阿摩尼阿斯这样  阿摩尼阿斯那样
Ammonius this, Ammonius that. Ammonius, Ammonius, Ammonius.
今天他对我说得极快
Today, he spoke to me
非常快  我不得不请求他说慢点
so quickly, I had to ask him slow down.
告诉我
Tell me something.
你认为我们是错的吗?
Do you ever think we're mistaken?
为什么这么说?
Why?
我曾被宽恕过
I always forgive and,
但现在  我无法宽恕别人
but now, I can't forgive.
宽恕
Forgive?
谁?
Who?
犹太人吗?
The Jews?
耶稣在十字架上宽恕了他们
Well, Jesus pardon them on the cross.
耶稣是上帝
Jesus was God
只有他才有这种宽容心
and only He can show such clemency.
你怎么敢拿自己跟上帝相提并论
How dare you compare yourself to God?
兄弟
Brother.
我们现在还活着
We are still alive.
因为什么?
Why?
因为
Because it was
是上帝的旨意  让我们没被石头打死
His will to save us from the stones.
上帝让我们在此  行该做之事
God wants us here, doing what we do.
你不再相信这些了吗?
Don't you believe in that anymore?
阁下
My Lord,
西里尔是个骄傲的男人
Cyril is a very proud man.
他同意会面  但只协商和平议题
He'll agree to meet, but he wouldn't discuss the Jews,
不商讨犹太人问题
only discuss peace.
和平
Peace?
作为您卑微的参谋  我的建议是
My suggestion, as your humble adviser in this affair,
请您接受提议
is for you to accept.
和平是最重要的
Let peace be foremost.
-老师  你怎么看?  -我
-Lady, what do you think? -Well,I,
我觉得这个提议并没有那么好
I don't think it's very encouraging.
为什么他来见俄瑞斯特斯?
Why would he want to come and see Orestes without any concrete proposals?
而且还有别的东西
And there's something else.
他要来见你
He won't come to you.
但需要你在图书馆和他见面
Demands he meet you in the Library,
在星期天的礼拜中
during the Sunday service.
在图书馆吗?  为什么?
In the Library? Why?
那次抢占之后
Only Christians are being permitted to enter the Library
只有基督徒才能进入图书馆
since it was stoned.
这是挑衅
It is a provocation!
请允许我说几句
Allow me to suggest.
如果你觉得你的到场
If you consider your presence
是如此的重要
so essential
为什么你不接受洗礼呢?
why not let yourself be baptized?
我们中的大多数人
The majority of us here,
包括最高长官  都已经接纳了基督教
beginning with our prefect, have accepted Christ.
剩余的这些人为什么不行呢?
Why not the rest of you?
这只是个时间问题  你们心知肚明
It's only a matter of time and you know it!
是吗?
Really?
这真的只是个时间问题吗?
It is just a matter of time?
请容许我说几句
Well, excuse me,
尊敬的元老  但据我所知
honored member but as far as I'm aware
你们的上帝并不能证明他自己
your God has not yet proved himself
比他的前任们更公正更仁慈
to be more just or more merciful than his predecessors.
老师
Lady.
让我接受你们的信仰  真的只是时间问题吗?
Is it really just a question of time before I accept your faith?
那是什么?
Why, then,
难道这次会议
should this assembly
要接受一个毫无信仰的人
accept the counsel of someone who admittedly
提出的提议吗?
believes in absolutely nothing?
我信仰哲学
I believe in philosophy.
哲学
Philosophy.
正是现在这种时候
Just what we need
我们所需要的东西
in times like this.
够了
Enough!
这些年来  我一直在研究
All these years, I've been studying.
完全没有了自己的生活
With absolutely no life of my own.
我想知道  我这样为了什么?
And I wonder, what was the point?
忘了今天那些话吧
Whoa, forget about what was said today.
是生活困住了我吗?
Is this all life holds for me?
还能是什么?
What else?
我觉得没人能看出
I doubt anyone could see as a,
你是一位忠诚的妻子
devoted wife
一位尽心的母亲
and mother.
我认为
I think,
城里的所有人都听说了手帕的故事
I think everyone in the city knows the story of the handkerchief.
所以
So,
我父亲也会喜欢女人
My father loved a woman.
连他也不例外
Even he,
有谁不爱呢?
Who have I ever loved?
除了你
Except you,
黎巴农斯
Libanius.
如果我能
If I could just,
解开这个谜团
just unravel this,
只需要再多努力一点
just a little bit more.
只要离答案再接近一些  那么
And just get a little close to the answer then,
这样  我就能
then I would,
我就能安然入土
then I would go to my grave a happy woman.
为什么?
Why?
为什么这些对你如此重要?
Why does that mean so much to you?
就是现在
Right now,
就在这一秒  整个世界可能都在移动
this very second, the whole Earth could be moving
却没有人意识到这些
and no one realizes it.
只有你和我知道
Except you and me.
相信我  老师  幸亏没人意识得到
Believe me Lady, it's best no one does.
你觉得这些真的不重要吗?
Do you really not think it important?
我不明白你为什么
I don't understand
坚信人们脚下的土地是移动的呢
why you insist on moving the ground we walk on.
你也看到了船上发生的
Well, you saw for yourself what happened on the boat.
是的  但那也不能证明地球在移动
Yes, I did. But that does not necessarily mean the Earth moves.
如果确实是这样呢?
What if it does?
希帕蒂亚  看看你的周围
Hypatia, look around you.
死亡
Death,
恐惧
horror
毁灭
destruction.
如果地球真的在圆形轨道中移动
If the stars move in a circle
他们为什么  不把完美分给我们一些呢?
why would they share their perfection with us?
所以我们没有移动
So we do not move,
只是不在圆形轨道中
In a circle.
我们不是按照圆形
We don't move,
运动的
Circle.
我们并非在圆形轨道中移动
We do not move in a circle.
从柏拉图开始
Ever since Plato,
所有人  包括阿里斯塔克斯  希巴克斯  托勒密
all of them: Aristarchus Hipparchus, Ptolemy,
所有人都试图用圆形轨道
they have all tried to reconcile their observations
来解释他们的观察结果
with circular orbits but,
但如果在宇宙中隐藏着其它形状呢?
What if another shape is hiding in the heavens?
其它形状
Another shape?
女士  没有任何形状比圆形更完美
Lady, there is no shape purer than the circle.
这是你教我们的
You taught us that.
我知道  只是假设
I know, but suppose just suppose the,
正是圆形的完美
purity of the circle
让我们忽视了其它的一切
has blinded us from seeing anything beyond it.
就像耀眼的太阳让我们
The same way that the glare of the sun
看不见星星一样
blind us from actually seeing the stars.
我必须重新
I must begin all over with,
重新审视这个问题
with new eyes.
我必须重新思考一切
I must rethink everything.
所有的一切
I have to rethink everything.
从保罗写给提摩太的第一封信开始读
Reading from the first letter of Paul to Timothy.
我渴望男人  无处不在
I desire therefore, that everywhere
举起圣洁的手  随处祷告
men should lift up holy hands in prayer
无忿怒  无争论
without anger or disputing.
同样  又愿女人
In like manner, I desire women
廉耻  自守
to dress modestly,
以正派衣裳为妆饰
with decency and propriety
不以编发
not with braided hair
黄金  珍珠
or gold or pearls
和贵价的衣裳为妆饰
or expensive clothes,
-只要有善行  -为什么读这段?
-but with good deeds. -Why is he reading this passage?
不知道  首领
I don't know, prefect.
但我肯定这不是事先说好的那段
I assure you it is not the one we agreed on.
女人要沉静学道
That a woman learn
一味的顺服  我不许女人讲道
in quietness and in full submission. I do not permit a woman,
也不许他辖管男人
to teach or to have authority over a man,
只要
but to be
沉静
in silence.
这是上帝之言
This is the word of God!
阿门
Amen.
当耶稣把自己的神圣遗产
Jesus himself
托付给他的十二门徒时
knew this when he
他自己非常了解这些
entrusted his holy legacy to twelve men
全是男人
Men.
没有一个女人
Not a woman among them.
但是
And yet,
我知道亚历山大有些人
I know of some in Alexandria
他们仰慕某个女人并且对她的话
who admire and even trust
言听计从
in the word of a woman.
哲学家希帕蒂亚
The philosopher Hypatia.
这个女人曾公然表示过
A woman who declared,
她对上帝的不忠
in public, her ungodliness.
她是个女巫
A witch!
官员们
Dignitaries,
你们现在应该全部信奉基督
it is time for you all to reconcile yourselves with Christ.
这是上帝之言
This is the word of God.
在圣经面前下跪  并接受真理吧
Kneel before it and embrace its truth.
跪下
Kneel.
他不准备跪下吗?
Is he not going to kneel?
跪下
Kneel!
罪人
Sinner!
我是基督徒
I am a Christian!
-我是基督徒  -不  你不是
-I am a Christian! -You're not a Christian!
我是和你们一样的基督徒
I'm as Christian as you are.
给提督让路
Make way for the prefect!
让路
Make way!
我是受过洗礼的基督徒
I am a baptized Christian!
我要杀了你
I'll kill you.
我是和你们一样的基督徒
I am as Christian as you.
I am as Christian as you are.
怎么会发生这种事
I mean, how could such a thing be possible?
罪犯已经被绳之以法了
The culprit has been executed.
立即带我去见提督
I would like you to take me to the prefect immediately.
女士  他亲自下令
Lady, he himself gave the order
让你待在家里等进一步的通知
for you to be confined to the house until further notice.
现在这种情况  我建议你  不要在街上出现
At the moment your presence on the streets is not advisable.
为什么?
For what reason?
西里尔对你进行了严厉的谴责
Cyril has made some serious accusations against you.
那么
And um,
他控诉我什么罪名?
What does he accused me of?
对上帝不虔诚
Ungodliness,
还有使用巫术
And witchcraft.
我知道了
I see.
你在为什么事而烦恼吗?女士
Is something bothering you, Lady?
没有
No.
不如你来告诉我你在担心什么?
Why don't you tell me what's worrying you?
提督  咬住这个
Prefect, why don't you bite on it?
说
Speak.
昔兰尼的主教想见您
The Bishop of Cyrene wishes to see you.
所有人都出去
All of you,
提督  伤口还没处理好
Prefect, the wound is not yet closed.
出去  出去
Get out. Get out!
所有人出去
All of you out! Out!
你们没能杀死我啊
Well, that went well.
你认为我也参与这件事了吗?
You think I had a part on this?
如果我想背叛你  怎么还会来到你面前
Would I show my face here if I wanted to betray you?
-你是瞎了吗?  -是的  我是瞎了
-Are you blind?  -I was, yes, I was blind.
他一直想要的
Well, it's my head.
是我的头  他想让我死
He's wanted all along, it's me,
随后就有了这次袭击
that snake is after.
这个政府
This government!
这座城市
This city!
听着
Now, listen.
-战争即将到来  -我知道
-War is brewing. I know.
我知道
I know.
那么宣誓对我效忠吧
Do you swear your loyalty to me?
向国家宣誓  快
To the Empire? Do it.
要么谴责他  要么滚出去
Condemn him or get out.
我会这么做的
I will do it.
如果有必要  我甚至会跪下来
On my knees, if necessary.
而且不只如此
And not only that.
几天之内  我可以召集其它省的主教
In a few days, I can gather other bishops from the province
和沙漠里的修道士们来对抗西里尔
and amongst from the desert all against Cyril.
但首先我要问你个问题
First, I must ask you a question.
俄瑞斯特斯  你相信耶稣吗?
Orestes, do you believe in Jesus?
你问我什么?
Do I what?
-你相信耶稣吗?  -你问我什么?
-Do you believe in Jesus?  -Do I what!?
你到底是真正的基督徒
Are you a true Christian?
还是你像那些寥寥众生  仅仅臣服于
Or did you like so many others, only convert
-自己的政治生涯  -辛奈西斯
-to prosper in politics? -Synesius.
你为什么不下跪?
Why didn't you kneel?
-我有什么选择?  -你为什么不下跪?
-What choice did I have? -Why didn't you kneel?
我还有什么选择?
What choice did I have?
背叛希帕蒂亚
Betray Hypatia?
谴责她吗?
Condemn her?
你会那么做吗?
Would you have done that?
我绝不会冒犯上帝的
I would never offend God.
是他  是他冒犯了上帝
It's he, he is offending God. He is offending him.
他在歪曲圣经
He's twisting his words
他在曲解圣经的意思
he's using the Scriptures.
他只是在宣读圣经
He read what is written.
有多少女人可以对你发号施令
How many women do you obey?
多少个?
How many?
你仰慕的同时  又能听你倾诉  的女人有几个
How many do you admire and listen to?
只有
Only
一个
One.
只有一个
Only one.
圣经
The Scripture,
圣经是正确的
The Scripture is correct,
只是由于在他的手中
and it was in His hands.
兄弟  你还不明白吗?
Brother, don't you see?
你不明白你那样做是在众人面前
Don't you see the insult to God?
侮辱上帝吗?
In front of everyone.
我不知道
I don't know,
我不知道该相信什么?
I don't know what, what I believe.
你必须告诉他
You have to tell him.
别跟我说  俄瑞斯特斯
Go tell him now, Orestes.
告诉上帝你相信圣经
Tell him you believe in what is written.
-我信奉  -别跟我说  去跟他说
-I believe, -Don't tell me. Tell Him.
告诉上帝
Tell God.
跪下
Kneel!
许多人至今都记得
Many are those who remember today the miracles
我们挚爱的兄长曾创造的奇迹
our beloved brother performed in life.
比如那次他将自己托付给圣父
Like the time he commended himself to the Father
踏过火堆却毫发无损
and threw himself into fire and was not even singe.
阿摩尼阿斯
Ammonius,
因为英勇捍卫对基督的信仰而献身
dead of bravely defending your faith in Christ.
我追封你为
I proclaim you a martyr.
圣徒
A saint.
从此以后你将会被人们称为
From now on, you shall be known as,
圣图梅西斯
Saint Taumasius.
我们要讨回公道
We want justice!
公道
Justice!
愿上帝指引我们  我亲爱的
May God show us the way,
圣战士们  我言尽于此
my dear parabolani. Little else can I say to you.
尼帝亚的修道士有多少
What about the monks of Nitria?
他们至少有500人  而且
We can win at least 500 of them.
我们还有500人
plus 500 of our own men,
你以为这就够了吗?  他可是地区提督
Do you think that's enough? He's the prefect,
都有的军队都会保卫他
He has a whole army to protect him.
听着
Listen!
我们何不找个简单又有效的方法
Why don't we do something much more simple and effective?
你指的是什么?
What are you talking about?
我们可以伤害他最关心的东西
We can hurt him where it hurts most,,,
如何?
How?
-那个婊子  -谁啊?
-That whore. -Who?
如果我们敢于面对世界的本相会怎样?
What if we dared to look at the world just as it is?
我们先摒弃那些先入为主的想法
Let us share for a moment every preconceived idea.
它会是什么形状?  什么形状?
What shape would it show us? What shape?
你曾说过问题在于太阳体积的不一致
You once said that the problem lies in the inconsistency of the sun.
没错  我说过  很好  说清楚一点
Yes I did, good,good Put it into words.
太阳一定要在中心  因为我们绕着它旋转
The sun must be at the center, since we revolve around it.
与此同时
And at the same time,
它又在其它位置  因为它离我们时远时近
in another position since our distance from it varies.
-没错  正是如此  -怎么会?
-Yes, exactly. -How?
它是如何同时占据两个位置的?
How could it occupy two positions?
怎么同时占据两个位置的?
How could I occupy two positions at once?
亚斯巴修
Aspasius,
没错  没错  就是那儿  另一个放在这儿
Yes, yes. There. And then the other one here.
保持相同的比例
Keeping the same proportion.
很好  把那端栓在火炬上
Good. Very good. Now, tie this end to that torch.
亚斯巴修
Aspasius.
我要你把这个想象成是地球
I want you to imagine that this is the Earth.
每把火炬代表
And that each of these flames represent
它距离太阳的两个极限位置
the two extreme positions of the sun in relation to it.
也就是冬天和夏天
In winter and in summer.
如果这两个位置都是同一个圆
What would happen if both these positions with the two centers
的圆心会是什么样
of one and the same circle?
这是不可能的  主人
But it is impossible, mistress.
等等  圆是什么?
Wait. What do we know about a circle?
我们知道圆心
We know that the center of a circle
到圆周上任一点的距离总是相等
is always the same distance from any point along its perimeter.
-没错  -是的
-Exactly. Yes, so,
那如果我们把这个圆心分成两个呢
What if I divide the center into two,
让圆周上的点到
but what I keep constant
这两个圆心的距离之和保持不变
is the sum of their two distances to the perimeter.
好吧  我给你演示一下  看着  当我沿着
Alright, look. I'll show you. Watch.  As I move this rod along
这个圆周移动棒子  绳子的一部分增加时
the cord, as one segment increases
另一部分就会减少  反之亦然
the other segment decreases, and vice versa.
因此两者之和
Therefore the sum of the two is always going to be constant.
保持不变  你明白了吗?
Do you see that?
如果我们把这个理论运用到
Now, what if we apply this
地球的移动之上呢?
to the movement of the Earth?
我们会
What,
得到
figure,
什么图形呢?
will be obtained?
一个椭圆轨道
An ellipse!
太阳在它的一个焦点之上
With the sun at one of its foci.
因为
Because,
这种椭圆轨道
what is a circle except
除了它的焦点太近以至于
a very special ellipse
看上去似乎合二为一了  还能是什么别的
whose foci have joined so close together that they appear to be one.
或许只是异想天开而已  亚斯巴修
Perhaps, I'm completely raving, Aspasius.
为什么非这样不可  也许我只是
I mean, why should this be so? Maybe I'm just,
也许我
Maybe I'm,
你怎么看?
What do you think?
很可能就是这样的  主人
It could well be solved, mistress.
太好了  我们明天再继续
Well done, we'll continue with this tomorrow.
去休息吧
Get some sleep.
-晚安  主人  -晚安
-Good night, mistress. -Good night.
谢谢你
Thank you.
达乌斯
Davus!
你在干什么?
What are you doing?
老师
Lady.
让我看看
Let me see.
你去那边坐下吧
Why don't you sit down?
大家都去哪了
Where is everybody?
请坐
Please sit down.
我有
I have,
我也有消息要告诉你
I have news for you too.
所有的已经皈依
All dignitaries
基督教的官员们
who have yet to embrace the Christian faith
将要在公众面前
are to be baptized
接受洗礼
in public.
目的非常明确
The aim very clear:
为了增加拥护者  使市里所有的基督徒
It's to add to our cause, all the Christians in the city
以及正派人士们
decent folk, better
都为我尽忠
to fight for me.
你指的是宣扬信仰吗?
You speak of battling faith.
非常好
Very well.
既然所有的事都已成定局
It seems everything seems to have been decided already.
我不懂你还让我来这里做什么?
I don't understand why you required my presence here.
我又不是政府的一员
I am not a member of government.
你不是  但你更重要  你是我最信任的人
No, you are more than that. You are the person I trust most
众人皆知
and everyone knows it.
你在说什么?
What can I say?
老师
Lady.
很多年前
Many years ago,
很多年前你教导我们
years ago, you taught us something.
如果
If,
等同于同量的量
If two are equal to a third they are,
彼此相等  还记得吗?
all are equal to each other. Do you remember?
是的
Yes
我们三个  我们都是好人
The three of us, we are all good people.
你和我们一样  都是虔诚的基督徒
And you, you are as Christian as we are!
辛奈西斯  你对你的信仰深信不疑
Synesius, you don't question what you believe.
但我不能
You cannot.
我必须怀疑
I must.
那真是太遗憾了
That's a pity,
老师
Lady.
莫大的遗憾
A great pity.
我们所尊敬的老师
Our revered teacher
竟然背弃了自己曾教给过我们的东西
taken away from what she herself taught us.
你以为我不知道你  所执迷那些愚蠢的事
Or do you think I'm not aware of the insane things you invoke.
-辛奈西斯  -地球围绕太阳旋转
-Synesius! With Earth moving around the Sun.
接下来又会是什么?  老师
What next, Lady, what next?
求你让我离开吧
You must let me go.
让我进去  让我进去
Let me in! Let me in!
-我有话对她说  -一个圣战士
-I'll go straight to her. -Why does she wanna see a parabolani?
-老师  -在我们逮捕你之前快滚
-Lady! Go away before we arrest you.
-走开  -亚斯巴修
-Leave! -Aspasius!
是我  达乌斯  达乌斯  放开我
It's me, Davus. Get off me.
-告诉他们你认识我  -你认识他吗?
-Tell them who I am -I know this man, please.
是的  你想干嘛?
What do you want?
我有话对她说  她在哪?
I need to speak to the mistress. Where is she?
-女主人不在家  -十万火急  她在哪?
-Mistress is not here. -It's urgent! Where is she?
她在提督宫殿里
She's at the prefect's palace.
-哪里?  -她在提督宫殿里
-Where? -The prefect palace!
-提督宫殿  -谢谢  快点滚
-Prefect's palace. -Thank you. Get out of here.
那到底是谁?
Who was that?
他以前是这儿的奴隶
He was a slave once.
等等  求你  等一下  求你了
Wait, please! Wait! I beg you.
如果你不同意的话  我就不能再保护你了
If you don't agree, I won't be able to protect you any longer.
我也不能和你交往
I won't be able to have dealings with you
甚至不能和你打招呼
neither greet you.
希帕蒂亚
Hypatia.
你还不明白吗?
Don't you see?
没有你我活不下去的
I can't go on without you.
我不行
I cannot.
没有你我无法打败西里尔
Without you, I can't defeat Cyril.
俄瑞斯特斯
Orestes.
西里尔已经赢了
Cyril has already won.
谢谢
Thank you.
但我不需要你们的保护
I do not need you.
达乌斯!
Davus!
兄弟  你要去哪里?
Brother! Where are you going?
我们找到她了
We found her!
婊子  快走
Come on, walk!
快走  罪人
Move it, sinner!
婊子
Whore!
妖女
Witch!
多神教的人渣
Pagan sinner!
走啊  快走
Move! Come on!
妖女
Witch!
把她扒光
Strip her naked!
站起来
Get up.
就这样  这样上帝  可以看清你的污秽  妖女
That's it. So that God can behold in all your filth, whore.
看清你如何蛊惑提督  娼妇
The way you knock the prefect so hard.
异教徒
Heathen!
娼妇
Whore.
看啊
Look,
她一点反应都没有
she's not reacting.
把刀子插进她的皮肤她就叫得出来了
She will scream all right when we skin her alive.
-有多少人有刀子  -没有
-How many of you have knives? -None.
不要让不洁的血液玷污你们的双手
Don't stain your hands with impure blood.
用石块砸死她吧
Let's stone her!
-我们用石块砸死这个妖女  -去找些石块
-Let's stone this witch! -Get some stones.
-快点  我们扔俄瑞斯特斯的石头
-Quickly! The ones we throw at Orestes.
还在这里
they are still here.
我看着她
I'll stay with her.
她晕过去了
She fainted.
希帕蒂亚的尸体残缺不全  留下的部分
The body of Hypatia was mutilated and the remains,
被拖去游街  焚烧
were dragged through the streets and burned in a fire.
俄瑞斯特斯被永久性的放逐  而西里尔,
Orestes was outlawed forever and Cyril,
则掌握了亚历山大的大权
took control of the power in Alexandria.
不久之后  西里尔被封为圣徒  教会圣士
Later, Cyril was declared a Saint and Doctor of the Church.
尽管希帕蒂娅的成果  没有被保存下来
Although not any of Hypatia works remains,
但她仍然被后人当作杰出的天文学家
it is known that she was an exceptional astronomer,
并且以对圆锥曲线的研究而著称
well-known for the mathematical study of conical curves.
1200年后
One thousand two hundred years later,
17世纪  天文学家约翰内斯・开普勒
in the 17th century, astronomer Johannes Kepler,
解释了圆锥曲线之中的
described that one of those curves,,
椭圆  正是它主宰着星球的运动轨迹
the ellipse, governs the movement of the planets.